We've talked a lot about props.
We talked about emits.
And so something you might be thinking, though,
is that, well, OK, this is my mixed sense, right?
I can pass data down to my components.
But at some point, this might get cumbersome.
And so I want to give you a microversion of the button
exercise that I give in the production grade view workshop.
So if you want to check that out for this.
But let's, for a second, think of a component.
Let's go ahead and depict this out real quick as a base button.
And so for this base button, you probably
are thinking, well, it's a button component.
And what kind of props would I want to pass to it?
Well, if we think about it, we can say, well, usually, you
need to have some text on your button.
So OK, let's call that a text prop.
And then I'll do the shorthand typing right now.
So this is an alternative, by the way, for props,
where if you don't want to do the required in default,
you just pass the type directly like this.
But again, generally speaking, I think
it's the best practice to define whether it's required
or if it's not required and has a default.
Basically, do your due diligence on that.
It helps your team in the long run.
OK, so you're like, OK, well, there might be some text here.
And then what happens if your product manager is like,
you know what, I think I want to use the icons on the left-hand
side.
Then you're like, oh, OK, maybe icon left string.
Or maybe just icon, right?
Because you're like, oh, OK, it has an icon.
It has an icon.
It's going to the left.
And then they go, well, actually,
it depends because the icon might be on the left or the right.
And then you might start getting the hint
of where I'm going with this.
But then you're like, OK, well, icon right.
And for now, I'm just keeping it simple,
just keeping these strings.
So I was like, OK, string.
And then all of a sudden, it's like, well, I also
need this to replace a loading spinner in case it's
like fetching an API call.
And all of a sudden, what you got here
is this massive list of props for what is really
just a button component, especially for something
like this text here.
Can you imagine how complicated the v if else if is going to be
when it's like, if loading, if loading shows this, but else
this, but then also if there's an icon,
then do this, this button will become very, very troublesome
to manage.
And so of course, Vue has an answer for this.
And the answer for this is around the idea of slots.
And so slots are an interesting concept
in that we have been using them this whole time when
it comes to HTML.
So how does a slot work?
Well, let's go ahead and just show you how.
Let's just refactor this real quick.
So icon, let's do this, icon text.
So I just want to have something that will render on the page.
And then we'll say, OK, so let's go.
Actually, since this is a playground,
let me move the base button to playground
so that this can be consistent.
Base button is going to source, going to components.
There we go.
Perfect.
And then to keep that consistent,
we'll just do base button in kebab case.
We'll hide that.
And then now let's make sure I'm running the playground app
so we don't run the wrong one.
Because nothing's more infuriating
than thinking being in the wrong environment
and thinking your code's not changing.
OK, so we have a base button here, app.vue.
So import base button, base button from here, base and button.
And then this is supposed to be base counter.
OK, how does base button work at the moment?
It is base button.
And we can give it a text of hi and the icon of arrow.
OK, so what happened?
Oh, I think I did not close it.
There we go.
OK, we see it here, right?
It says arrow and hi.
Great.
What we want to avoid when it comes to props
is being overly descriptive with how something
is supposed to be used.
It's useful for guidance.
It's useful as a guardrail.
But when it comes to something like what text belongs in a button,
it doesn't often make sense to do something like that with a prop.
So instead, what do we do?
Well, there is a built-in element called slot.
And so it's globally available to your app at all times
because this is a view component.
And slot, if we think about it, it actually
functions just as you would expect when it comes to HTML.
You just didn't realize it.
So rather than being like, oh, I wanted to say arrow and then
dash hi, this is a base button.
And we call it like a normal component.
And we say arrow, left, and hi.
And if you're looking at this going like, isn't that HTML?
I'd say exactly.
It's just like HTML.
Why complicate things beyond that, right?
There are times where you just want to let people just
define whatever they want inside of your component.
Now, granted, eventually you could do some fancy things
regarding maybe some props.
Maybe there is a point where you have some base icon here,
for example.
But slots are one of the most powerful features of view
in the sense that it allows for flexibility.
It's almost like in that regard, the complete opposite
of props, where props are being very prescriptive.
Do this with this type.
This is required.
Do it in this place.
Slots is saying, all right, I'm open.
Like, you can basically work with me here.
And so the cool thing about slots, too,
is that slots are more intelligent than a standard HTML
element in that you can actually provide it
a default content.
So what we can do is we can say, yeah, so we'll just
call it submit by default.
And so when you do that, this means
that when I go ahead and delete what's inside,
you'll notice it automatically falls back to that content,
which, again, can be very nice for just providing
some conventions, especially when people start having design
systems and that sort of thing.
It's like, OK, most of our buttons are submit.
We can go ahead and say, OK, all base buttons
have a default of submit.
But otherwise, the moment someone needs to override it,
easy peasy.
This is no longer submit.
This is now cancel.
As you can see, updates, just as you would expect.
And you can bind that, obviously, to your data?
Yep, exactly.
So the question here is around, can we do more than this?
Yeah, because we should treat this just
like any other HTML element.
So in here, we can do something like user data dot name.
And there you go.
It just works.
That's one of the things that always excites me.
When I look at how Views APIs design is extensibility
on what people already understand,
and then just leveraging the heck out of it.
Why not?
Why not sprinkle on some syntactic sugar, some superpowers
that make it even easier, right?
Because, again, slots inherently already
work from an HTML perspective.
But now you can provide default content.
We can actually do if conditions for slots, too.
So if you have something called direction,
and let's say directions here, and we can say v if left.
We could use slot for v else.
And then, so let's say the default is actually this submit.
But otherwise, if it has a configured prop of left,
it might be icon left, whatever, cancel.
And so what you get here is I'm already overriding it.
But if you come in here, save, you'll
see that submit is falling back as we would expect.
But if we have, whoop, I think my v if direction doesn't
make sense.
Actually, I can just do left.
It's fine.
So I do left is a Boolean, and the default is false.
So like that, you see submit does come up.
And then we can say left is true.
Icon left, cancel.
So that's pretty cool, but what else can we do?
There's even more, because if we think of slots
like a mailbox slot, we might want
to have multiple slots on a component, not just one.
And so what if we were to do something like layouts?
Well, if you had a layout component,
let's say I'm going to do baseLayout.View.
What you're probably going to end up having
is you probably have some sort of div
that is your class wrapper, assuming you
have a design system.
But then you might want to start figuring out
where things are being slotted.
So for example, you might have an aside here that
is class like sidebar.
And then you probably have somewhere
where you want to render out your main content.
And then you probably have your footer content.
And so again, if you do this by traditional props
and that kind of stuff, it gets really painful,
because how do you pass components into props?
Like that's just a whole messy matter.
But what we can do is we can give our slots names.
So this can be the sidebar slot.
This can be the main slot.
And this can be the footer slot.
And so the way this would work is,
if we're inside of our app.view, we
can go ahead and import base, let's see,
let me duplicate this one.
And then boom, boom, base layout from base layout.
We organize that to be alphabetical, great.
OK, then we get our base layout.
What we can do now is we can now define specific snippets
of HTML to go in specific places.
How do we define HTML?
We have our template element.
And so I know it's like, whoa, there's a template
and a template.
But again, if you look at MDN, template
is an actual HTML element.
It's a content template element.
Like this is a thing.
I think a lot of people at one point
was like, oh, that looks like a view thing.
No, this isn't the MDN docs.
This is fairly standard.
And so what we can do is we can say, look, this is the aside.
And how do we tell the template that we want to go there?
Well, we do the vslot directive.
And we tell it the, I believe this is aside like this.
And so if this renders correctly, base layout, oh, wait,
I did not.
Oh, I called it sidebar.
So of course, there's nowhere to go.
So I misnamed it sidebar aside.
There we go.
And so let's give this just a little bit of styling
just so that we can see the difference.
So let's go ahead and give the sidebar border 2px solid red.
And then we'll go ahead and do the same for each one.
So we'll have main.
And then we'll have footer.
And so we'll make this green.
We'll make this blue.
And so you can see right now, because nothing's
being passed to the slot for main or footer,
nothing's being rendered, just the aside.
And so all we got to do now is we can go ahead and add things
like template vslot main.
And then I can even do things like actually render the user
card.
Actually, I could even just take this component right here.
Let's take the user card here and just drop it directly
inside of main.
And so you can see here that it's actually being rendered
inside, although where did my borders go?
Main class.
Oh, I didn't give it a class.
Class main.
There we go.
Did you have a question?
I was wondering if the components that are not the slots
render in the DOM when you bring that template in.
So you're saying that if I don't.
So currently you have nothing in the footer slot.
Yep.
Is there a footer element?
Ah, good question.
And the answer is yes, it is there.
Because as far as view is concerned, what you're saying
is this is the scaffold expected to render.
There's nothing.
Well, yeah, I guess it would be a little bit tricky
as far as checking to make sure the slot, whether the slot is
empty or not.
So at that point, though, I'm saying that I would say
that if you're starting to get conditional about what
content is showing inside, at that point,
it would make more sense to make a slot name of a slot of
footer, for example.
And then maybe the default is to have some content in here,
but then otherwise let someone completely override it.
And then that way, if there is no slot, nothing shows up at
all.
That's probably the way I would approach it in that
particular case.
So here we go.
We have that.
Whoops, what did I forget?
There we go.
Boom.
So we can see now the footer actually is rendering.
And so all I've got to do now is do the template vslot
footer inside of here.
And then let's drop the base counter in there.
And so slots become really powerful, because if you've
ever worked with a backend CMS where users are defining
layouts, now you have the ability to, when you're fetching
data, to actually drop things where they're supposed to go
as opposed to having to configure like, oh, this is my
two-column layout.
This is my three-column layout.
This is my two-column with one.
There comes a point where that becomes very tedious to
maintain.
And slots do a lot in terms of opening up a lot of
reusability and composability when it comes to that.
What's cool about this, too, is that because it's
programmatic in terms of assigning its property,
it doesn't have to appear in a certain order.
So for example, I'll just swap these to show that.
You'll see that even though technically inside of here we've
ordered it as a side, main, whatever, it's totally being
controlled at this level.
And so as a result, you can, again, it just allows for more
composability and flexibility when it comes to that.
And the other thing I want to leave you off with before we
dive into exercises and other questions is that if you're
looking at some other code bases, not everyone writes out
the vslot directive.
And this is a convention within view three in that you can
shorthand it to just the hashtag symbol.
The way to think about it is like the idea of the slot that
you want to put the template stuff in.
To be honest, I find it a little bit confusing because if
someone doesn't know what this is and tries to Google this,
sometimes they might end up with CSS stuff.
This shorthand, personally, I don't tend to use it.
Again, it is in code bases, which is why I'm telling you
all this exists.
So that's your team's convention.
I would say roll with it.
Personally, though, I don't mind actually being explicit
about slot sidebar.
I think this, to me, is expressive.
And personally, that's what I prefer.